<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian unity exhorted to being a few words in tender love to all professing of Christianity in old England, the land of my nativity : wherein the difference between profession and possession of that which is really the substance of true religion, is clearly manifested : also, the great breach of Christian charity, caused by their furious contentions about formality : with a few words to the poor in spirit, concerning my opinion of a saving knowledge of Christ Jesus / by one who dearly loves all those whose conversation becomes Christ's Gospel.</title>
            <author>One who dearly loves all those whose conversation becomes Christ's Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32894</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R270</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12952450</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12952450</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32894)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 733:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian unity exhorted to being a few words in tender love to all professing of Christianity in old England, the land of my nativity : wherein the difference between profession and possession of that which is really the substance of true religion, is clearly manifested : also, the great breach of Christian charity, caused by their furious contentions about formality : with a few words to the poor in spirit, concerning my opinion of a saving knowledge of Christ Jesus / by one who dearly loves all those whose conversation becomes Christ's Gospel.</title>
                  <author>One who dearly loves all those whose conversation becomes Christ's Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95971:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95971:1"/>
            <p>Chriſtian Unity EXHORTED TO: BEING A few Words in tender love to all Profeſſing of Chriſtianity in Old <hi>England,</hi> the Land of my Nativity.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The difference between Profeſſion and Poſſeſſion of that which is really the ſubſtance of True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is clearly manifeſted.</p>
            <p>ALSO, The great Breach of Chriſtian Charity, cauſed by their furious Contentions about Formality.</p>
            <p>With a few words to the Poor in Spirit, concerning my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a ſaving knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>By one who dearly loves all thoſe whoſe Converſation becomes Chriſt's Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Epheſ. 4. Ver. 1.2, 3.</bibl> I therefore the priſoner of the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, with all lowlineſs and meekneſs, with long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in love, endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:95971:2"/>
            <head>Moderate Reader,</head>
            <p>'TIS my hearts deſire that all might come to know the difference between the Form and the Power of Godlineſs, which is the only Foundation of true Religion; not that I do in the leaſt imagine that all are in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but becauſe I have obſerved that the generality of Chriſtians are chiefly contending about the form; and the greateſt animoſity, that I ever heard or read of, have been cauſed by their different Opinions in that matter: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to the knowledge the Lord hath been pleaſed to beſtow upon me, 'tis my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that if the Power of Godlineſs were more exalted, and the Form leſs regarded, our love towards God and our Neighbor would be more augmented. Reader, I doubt not but ſome have written largely on the ſame ſubject (however new faſhions and new Books are moſt pleaſing to the curious pallates of theſe times;) but I have found more of Controverſie than true Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in many of them; for 'tis moſt certain that Logick tranſlated into Divinity, hath ſet all Christendom on fire. And he that can frame Syllogiſms in the vindication of his Opinion, is reputed the best Chriſtian, although he be but a
<pb facs="tcp:95971:2"/>cold well diſciplin'd. Thus hath true Religion imongſt Christians (ſo called) been almoſt (if not altogether) eztinguiſhed, Chriſtian fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip confounded, and Charity (which no true Chriſtian can want) buried in oblivion: Thus have they by their implacable contests about the Form, diſputed themſelves out of the true knowledge of the Power of Godlineſs: witneſs the ſenſuality, earthly mindedneſs, and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs that most Profeſſors are poſſeſsed with. Friendly Reader, 'tis not my deſire to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate the minds of any; for moderation is that which I chiefly aim at; therefore I pray be impartial in judging what thou readeſt, and when thy mind is retired, thou wilt find a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſenſe in thy ſelf of the truth of what is written: then may we praiſe and magnifie the name of our God, to whom Glory; Honour, Praiſe, and Obedience is due, now and for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 13th. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95971:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHen I conſider'd the diverſity of opinions amongſt nominal Chriſtians, I could not but conſult the cauſe, which being found, the effect was not ſtrange; for the Devil hath been that Jeſuit which hath ſown the feed of Diviſion amongſt men in former and latter Ages; and where the Notion of a Diety is not totally extinguiſhed, the Creature is a framing to it ſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may have the form of Divine worſhip, wherein perhaps may be perceived ſome ſeeming ſatisfaction which Induceth many to make a large profeſſion of it, but the Soul not being ſatisfied with ſhadows, puts them on ſeeking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe that may be more fatisfactory; ſo after many years Travel in the wilderneſs, they return empty, lamenting their loſt time, ſpent in that which profiteth not; the ſence of which cauſeth them to enter into a ſerious contemplation, at which time the ſtill voice of the ſpiritual Shepherd (Jeſus Chriſt) whiſpers to the Soul, if thou art thirſty I will give thee of the water of life freely, after which thou ſhalt never thirſt, for it ſhall be in thee a Well of water ſpringing up to everlaſting life, ſo all the faculties of the Soul ſhall be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Heavenly food, for he is the Heavenly bread which alone can ſatisfie the hungry Soul; he is the true living ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance moſt to be deſired; all outward elementary ſubſtances can but gratifie the ſenſual part of man; but ſuch hath been the deplorable ſtate of many Nations, ſince the great Apoſtacy from that pure Spiritual worſhip ſo much exhorted to by Chriſt and his Diſciples, that the Lord hath ſuffered a Cloud of darkneſs to over-ſpread the underſtandings of the children of men, ſo that they have been a long time grovel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the dark among the earthly Elements, pleaſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Pictures of Divine worſhip, making ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95971:3"/>great profeſſions of the form, they deny the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and have deſtroyed thouſands of each other, becauſe their Emblems of Divine worſhip did not agree in likeneſs; how contradictory this is to a ſerious, humble, ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, meek Spirit, let the ſober Reader judge.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore 'tis the deſire of my Soul, that every one that profeſſeth the name of Chriſt ſhould walk worthy of him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> endeavouring with all lowlineſs, meekneſs, long ſuffering, and forbearing one another, in love to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace; therefore way a with all ſtriving and contending about matters that are only circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall, forbear impoſing that on each other which cannot freely be received by either, exclaim not againſt each other, becauſe your Opinions do not agree in all particulars; but labour more and more after Unity rather then Uniformity; let all Controverſie be ended, ſince it lies not in your power to bring each others mind into one mould, deſire earneſtly of the Lord to mould them into one. Ah dear Friends how helpful would you then be to each other in exalting the glory of God, and ready would the Lord of life be to water you with his bleſſings, that you may encreaſe more and more with love to each other; and this certainly will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the deſign of the great Enemy of our Souls Salvation; whoſe deſign hath been chiefly to cauſe Diſſentions amongſt us: Oh that our moderation might be known to all men, that Chriſtian Fellowſhip may be renewed, and our confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with one another more Heavenly, that vain Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be prevented; Oh let us rather declare to each other what the Lord hath done for our Souls; how he hath filled us with ſpiritual joyes. How! ſweet are the ſtreams of Divine love: How! exceedingly pleaſant is the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of his countenance, how are all the faculties of our Souls raviſhed with his Beauty, Oh then may not we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare theſe things to worldly men that their affections may be more Heaven-ward. Dear Friends, theſe are not hearſays cull'd out of Books of mens inventions, but they are the precious fruits of Gods holy Spirit; or as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, the taſting of the Heavenly Gift, which is a living power from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95971:4"/>whence all our Spiritual comforts ariſe; the knowledge whereof is one of the chiefeſt principles which conſtitutes a true Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Friendly Reader, theſe are the rich poſſeſſions of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, this indeed is the very ſubſtance of Religion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, that man that enjoyes the ſubſtance may be a Chriſtian without the form, but no man with the form can be a Chriſtian without the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Moderate Reader, notwithſtanding I have contemned the formes of Religion, I do not condemn all perſons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing any of the ſeveral forms; for there are ſome who have much of Gods power accompanying them in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal performances, but no longer then the power of the mind and all the faculties of the Soul are joyned with them; my Opinion is of that latitude which extends to all who deſire to have a ſaving knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; notwithſtanding I cannot but reprove thoſe who content themſelves with a bare Hiſtorical faith, and indeed 'tis to be feared that there are too too many have no other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for their Chriſtianity, then a verball repetition of their Creed, commonly called a confeſſion of Faith; how far is this from that which purifies the heart, and obtains ſuch victory over ſin, even to the removing of Mountains of corruptions; let any ſober Chriſtian judge: but Chriſts own Teſtimony ſufficeth; for he ſaith, he that believeth in him, out of his belly ſhall flow Rivers of living waters; therefore it manifeſtly appears, that, that faith which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth not theſe effects, is not the true faith.</p>
            <p>A few words to the poor in ſpirit, who have been weary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Travelling on the barren Mountains, and do now earneſtly deſire to know the true way.</p>
            <p>It being my own condition in times paſt, I cannot but ſympathize with thee who ever thou art that haſt been wandering in by paths, whilſt we pretend to know the true way; therefore it manifeſtly appears that we wanted a true acquaintance with, and a ſpiritual knowledge of Chriſt, who declared himſelf to be the way and the life; Let us but reaſon together, Was not the knowledge we had of Chriſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95971:4"/>only Notional? had we any other evidence of faith in him, but a bare aſcent to what we have heard and read concerning him? what did it all amount to? what ſatisfaction had we? only a groundleſs hope of Salvation, becauſe many others whom we ſuppoſed good Chriſtians were of the ſame faith: we had hopes to be ſaved by Chriſts merits, hope after from puniſhment; but what experience had we of the virtue of Chriſts redeeming power out of ſin here? he came not only to ſave us from the puniſhment, but dominion of ſin, and to bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Now if thou art not wedded to thy former profeſſion, and haſt a true deſire after the ſaving knowledge Chriſt Jeſus the only Saviour of the world, I ſhall (according to the meaſure of knowledge given me of God,) plainly and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately declare what I believe to be a ſaving knowledge of him; alſo what I have experienced of the benefits flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him: firſt thou muſt know him to be at the door of thy heart by his inviſible and eternal Spirit, at all times according to St. <hi>Johns</hi> Teſtimony: Behold I ſtand at the door and knock, if any one will open to me, I will come into him and ſup with him, and he with me.</p>
            <p>Friendly Reader, how many Days, Weeks, Months, and Years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reve.</hi> 3.20.</note> hath our dear Saviour been knocking at the doors of our hearts, and we have paſſed it by, thinking't was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the checks of a natural conſcience: How! often have we vexed, grieved, and pierced, his holy ſpirit, how! often have we crucified him afreſh by rejecting and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Heavenly counſel; how have we turned a deaf ear to all his reproofs; and all was becauſe we had not a true ſence of his being ſo nigh to us, but were a ſeeking him where he was not to be found.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thou muſt know him to be thy Teacher, and reprover: 'tis his ſpirit and not a natural conſcience that checks thee for every evil thought, word, and deed; how often haſt thou been made to cry, Lord forgive me, when no perſon in the world could accuſe thee; he it is that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs in all things that pertain to thy everlaſting wellfare, for he is always wooing and beſeeching thee to turn from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95971:5"/>the evil of thy ways,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12.</note> and if thou wilt but hearken to his inſtruction, thou ſhalt receive power to overcome all the Enemies temptations, for the wholy Scriptures of Truth teſtifie, that to as many as receive him he gives power to become the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thou muſt know that he alone works in thee all good acts which thou performeſt, ſo thou art but the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and he the workman; therefore all the honour of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good work is due to him, who worketh in us both to will, and to do all things that are pleaſing to his Heavenly Father; all therefore that he requires of thee, is to be on a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual watch, ſo that thou mayſt know when thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; for I teſtifie in Gods fear ſo long as thou art on thy ſpiritual watch thou ſhalt not think an evil thought, but thou ſhalt be ſenſible of his reproof. By this means friendly Reader thou wilt come to be more and more, inwardly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him whom thou didſt formerly know only by hearſay, then wilt thou cry out with <hi>Job.</hi> I have heard of thee before with the hearing of my ear, but now hath mine eyes ſeen thee; and the more thou comeſt acquainted with him, thou ſhalt experience the virtue of Chriſts purifying power, whereby thou ſhalt be more and more cleanſed from all thy droſs and corruption, and thoſe in whom he works righteouſneſs he will continually juſtifie, for the blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt will cleanſe us from all ſin: ſo that we may be made fit Heirs of that Kingdom, prepared for thoſe that are true believers; now dear friend thou wilt not be in want of outward repreſentation to bring thee in remembrance of Chriſt Jeſus, for the true real ſpiritual enjoyment of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will cauſe all ſhadows to vaniſh, and beggerly Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to melt away, for it is impoſſible (ſo long as thou art on thy ſpiritual watch) to be unmindful of him; otherwiſe thou mayſt take thy lot with the unwatchful Centinel, who (though <hi>well armed</hi>) is ſurpriſed with the Enemy, and taken Captive; this is the condition of many whom I believe to be true Chriſtians, for their being overcome by the enemy, is not becauſe they were falſe and hypocritical in what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, but becauſe they were ſometimes off their watch, for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95971:5"/>Chriſts Diſciples were not all Hypocrites, becauſe they ſlept when their Lord and Maſter commanded them to watch; yet I ſay, that unwatchfulneſs is reprovable in any, being a great duty exhorted to by Jeſus Chriſt; for he ſaid, what I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I ſay unto all, watch; and this comprehends all the <hi>directions</hi> which are conduceably to a holy life. Now my dear friend, I have in ſhort declared unto thee what my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, concerning a ſaving knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; it is not my deſire that thou ſhouldeſt vow Allegiance to my Dictates, or pin thy faith upon my ſleeve, as I doubt we have both, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo much formerly upon others; but my heart earns towards thee, that thou mayſt be perſwaded to hearken to the teachings of Chriſts ſpirit alone; and then thou wilt not need any of mans teaching; for the Scriptures of Truth teſtifie that no man knoweth the things of God ſave the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, which ſpirit is ready and willing to inſtruct thee in all things that are neceſſary for thee to know; ſo this is one great benefit thou ſhalt partake of by this inward acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with Chriſt, in knowing him to be with thee at all times, and in all places; Nay, when thou art in thy bed, (if thy mind be retired) he will make thee remember what thou haſt done in the day paſt, for he ſits in thy conſcience judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all thy actions; note therefore, that conſcience is not the Judge, but the Seat wherein the Judges ſits, therefore pray miſtake not the Seat for the Judge: for I cannot but make mention of this thing, becauſe of the great miſtake that thouſands are in about this matter; for when they have been afraid to commit ſome groſs ſin, they ſay their conſcience will not ſuffer them; not conſidering who it is that is in their conſciences reſtraining them from ſinning; ſo Chriſt hath been robbed of his honour, and many hundreds have been in want of his Divine power, becauſe they have not known him ſo near them. Friendly Reader, let me intreat thee when thou art in a ſerious frame of ſpirit, examine thy own heart, and I doubt not but thou wilt find ſome ſenſe of theſe things in thy own particular, and it ſhall be the deſire of my Soul, that the Lord may increaſe in thee more and more a lively power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſence of his Truths, that it may be to his glory, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95971:6"/>the everlaſting welfare of thy poor immortal Soul: and for thy farther ſatisfaction, ſearch the holy Scriptures, for I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to write any thing but what they teſtifie, and wait on the Lord alone for Direction and Counſel; therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult not with fleſh and bloud, and thou ſhalt receive an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſence of that which thou deſireſt to know; for the ſeeking that of mans wiſdom which alone belongs to the Revelation of Gods ſpirit, hath been the only cauſe that many have been always a learning, and yet never come to the knowledge of the Truth; friendly Reader, I doubt not if thou art one who deſires to be acquainted with the holy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Chriſts ſpirit, but that thou wilt have a clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding of the vaſt difference between thy ſeeking knowledge from the precepts of men, and the Revelations of Gods ſpirit; (too too much ſlighted by many in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) therefore pray let us beware of doing deſpite to the ſpirit of Grace? and reſiſting the Holy Ghoſt in working on our corrupt wills and affections, in order both to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and converſion; for though there is no power in our natural Wills to act that which is good, yet there is an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to refuſe reſiſting of that which hath power to work; otherwiſe how could it be ſaid in Scripture, that men grieve and quench the holy ſpirit of God, and reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, and turn from the grace of God to wantonneſs, which hath provoked the Lord to declare by his holy Prophets, that his ſpirit ſhould not always ſtrive with man; which makes me to conclude that there is a Paſſive, (though not an active) power in mans will; for certainly the Lord would not ſo much complain on the Children of men for rebelling againſt his good ſpirit, if they were not deſtitute of all power in yielding obedience to its holy operation; how did our dear and ever bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt lament the ſad ſtate and condition of the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>How would I have gathered you as a Hen gathereth her Chickens, under her wings, but you would not?</hi> which to me is a plain demonſtration that there was a poſſibility of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, as well as rejecting the tender offers of Chriſts love, and doubtleſs he would not have intreated them, were they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95971:6"/>wholly incapable of receiving his kind Intreaties. Oh there; fore Dear friends, our deſtruction is of our ſelves, for the Lord ſaid by his Holy Prophet in the days of old, why will you dye O Houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> clearly ſhewing forth that we our ſelves are the cauſe of our own deſtruction; Oh let us conſider, what could he have done more for us then he hath done, he hath written his holy Laws in our hearts, which are holy Rules for us to walk by; he hath ſent his only begotten Son to be our Mediator and Redeemer, that we may be ſaved from our ſins here, and the puniſhment due to them hereafter; he it is who is the Captain of our Salvation: but if we will not be his faithful Souldiers, we cannot expect his protection. Oh how great hath his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering been to us-ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance, and to the knowledge of his bleſſed Truths. Certainly had not our God been a God full of compaſſion, ſlow of anger, and of great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who retaineth not his anger for ever, but in wrath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth his mercy, becauſe his compaſſions fail not; we might have long ſince been deſtroyed, and been now roaring in endleſs wo and miſery; but bleſſed and for ever bleſſed be the name of our God whoſe mercy endureth for ever, that he hath been pleaſed to continue unto us a day of viſitation; whereby we have been made to cry out, what have I done, Lord, what have I done? How have I rejected the tender viſitation of thy love? how have I extinguiſhed the Divine motions of thy holy Spirit? how have I ſinned againſt thy loving kindneſs which is better then life? and abuſed all thy mercies? Oh therefore let us beware of letting ſlip the day of our viſitation, being there is an Eternity of felicity depends on our improving ſo gracious an oppertunity: but ſuch are the baſe inclinations of <hi>our</hi> corrupt natures, that we uſe all our dilligence, and watchfulneſs, rather to enjoy momentary pleaſure, then to make ſure our Calling and Election; how little do the generality of men regard that which is the moſt noble part of men, how earneſtly do they purſue their ſenſual delights, which have anxiety always for a companion. Oh that they would be perſwaded and entreated to ſet a part
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95971:7"/>ſome time for a ſerious contemplation on Eternity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be truly ſenſible of the ſad and dangerous ſtate that hitherto they have lived in; Oh that they would beware of being rocked aſleep in the Devils Cradle of carnal ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is a great cauſe that ſo many have diſ-regarded the knockings of Chriſts ſpirit at the door of their hearts; and if at any time they are made ſenſible of ſome groſs evil which they have acted, immediately they endeavour to ſtop the mouth of conſcience, either by hearkning to the Devils Lullabies, <hi>(viz.) Libidian</hi> Songs, or playing with his Rattles; otherwiſe ride abroad in his Chariots of ſenſual pleaſures, in which they are frequently carried to the Gates of death; ſo the deſtruction of body and ſoul is the ſad conſequence which certainly attends thoſe who are (as it were ſwallowed up of worldly pleaſures.</p>
            <p>But oh man who ever thou art that haſt been hitherto led away by the Enemy of thy immortal ſoul, who would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly make thee his aſſociate in eternal miſery, be perſwaded and intreated to take eſpecial notice of theſe following words: firſt let not the Devil tempt thee to imagine, that 'tis too late to turn from the evil of thy ways, becauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thou haſt been an old ſinner. Secondly, let not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity of thy corrupt will and affections, to folly and vanity induce thee to think the time too ſoon. Thirdly, let not the multiplicity of thy ſins which thou haſt not in times paſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of affright thee; for be aſſured at whatſoever time thou hearken'ſt to the ſtill voice of Chriſts ſpirit in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which ſecretly rebukes thee, and tells thee all things that ever thou didſt, thou ſhalt find thy heart ſorrowful for ſin, and as thou keepeſt on thy watch, thou ſhalt be brought more and more into a tender frame of ſpirit, and thou ſhalt be enabled to turn from thy ſin, perfectly, abhorring thoſe things which formerly thou didſt ſo much delight in, and thou ſhalt aſſuredly receive pardon for all thy ſins paſt be they never ſo many and great, according to the words of Chriſt Jeſus,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, He that heareth my word, and believeth in him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation:</hi> for thoſe ſins which Chriſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95971:7"/>pardons in this life ſhall never be charged to thy account any more,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 18.21,</note> according to the words the Lord ſpoke to the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ezekiell: But if the wicked will turn from all the ſins he hath committed, and keep all my Statutes, and do that which is lawfull and right, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye. All his tranſgreſſions which he hath committed, they ſhall not be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned unto him.</hi> Now therefore thou mayſt ſee what great encouragemet all perſons have to turn from their ſins; Oh that theſe things were more ſeriouſly conſider'd by all that profeſs Chriſtianity, they would certainly be more diligent in improving thoſe golden opportunities, which the Lord through his infinite love and mercy hath allowed them.</p>
            <p>Friendly Reader, for thy farther encouragement, if thou wilt but take a walk with me in the withdrawing Room of holy Meditation, thou ſhalt have a Soul-raviſhing proſpect into the Garden of Heavenly joy, where thou ſhalt behold the ſtreames of Grace flowing from the fountain of Divine love; and thou ſhalt drink freely out of the ſprings of life, which alone can ſatisfie the appetite of a thirſty Soul; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be entreated and perſwaded no longer to continue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy ſelf in the dead Pictures of Religion, which hath made thee ignorant of thoſe ſpiritual enjoyments, which alone belongs to the life and power of Chriſtianity, and for which reaſon many may be ignorant of what I now write: therefore thoſe that would be of the true Religion, muſt ſtand no longer on the barren Mountains of profeſſion, but rather hearken to the voice of the ſpiritual Shepherd, who will certainly lead them into the pleaſant fields amongſt the green Paſtures, wherein grows the flowers of Heavenly joy, and through which runs the pleaſant Rivers of conſolation, ſo that thou mayſt with joy draw water out of the well of Salvation, whereby thy ſoul ſhall be compleatly refreſhed, then ſhall all her faculties (which have long languiſhed for want of true ſubſtance) be revived; then ſhall ſhe be fully ſenſible of the difference between her true teacher and leader, and the falſe guides, who had carryed her into the wilderneſs, where ſhe had been a long time afflicted with trouble and ſorrow; then will her bowels be filled with pity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95971:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>on all thoſe who did formerly accompany her in her diſtreſſed condition, and will be grieved that any ſhould be ſo deceived as not to be perſwaded to hearken to the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual voice, whereby they may partake of the ſame ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial food; but rather chooſe to feed on the husk of Religion, then to partake with her of thoſe glorious refreſhments, which cauſeth her to be always praiſing and magnifying the name of the Eternal God, at whoſe right hand are pleaſure for ever more.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A few words to thoſe who are totally ignorant of ſpiritual things.</head>
               <p>That there are many in the Land of my Nativity who are totally ignorant of ſpiritual things, I may boldly affirm; but that 'tis in the power of any mortal man to give them a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual diſcerning I utterly deny; Notwithſtanding it ſeems to me very expedient to remove all obſtacles out of the way of the ignorant, leaſt their miſ-apprehenſion of words cauſe a diſ-ſatisfaction to the matter, which otherwiſe being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pained with a Divine power, might prove beneficial to them; therefore according as the Lord enables me, I ſhall endeavour to anſwer with all plainneſs thoſe objections which are of moſt weight.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1ſt.</label> Firſt, therefore it may be required, how I underſtand Chriſt to be in all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer that according to the common acknowledgement of all Chriſtians, as he is God, his Spirit is Omnipreſent, for the Heavens and Earth cannot contain him, and if his ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity fills the Heavens and all Created beings, then man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Creature muſt in ſome meaſure receive of his fulneſs; but more particularly, as he is the Son of God the only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World, he is in all men, though at the ſame time the fulneſs of the Godhead is in the Heaven of Heavens at the right hand of his Father, for he doth communicate a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his ſpirit unto all every individual perſon in order to their inſtruction or reproof: <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7, 8. <hi>Nevertheleſs I tell you, it is expedient for you that I go away; for if I go not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the comforter will not com: ebut if I depart I will ſend him unto you, and when he is come, he will remove the World of ſin,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95971:8"/>of righteouſneſs, and of judgement.</hi> Joh. 14.15. <hi>But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will ſend in my nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, he ſhall teach all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatſoever I have ſaid;</hi> therefore 'tis evident, that Chriſt is by his Spirit in every man, reproving and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing them, and bringing all things that he hath former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to their and our remembrance. But for a farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration I ſhall uſe this one compariſon, As the natural Son in in the firmament doth communicate its light to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the world, at one and the ſame time, though thouſands of miles aſunder, and yet the body or whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion remains entire in the firmament without any dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution; ſo doth the glorious Son of righteouſneſs, though ſitting in his Kingly Throne, communicates a meaſure of his own ſpirit to every-man to profit with all; which ſpirit is oftentimes in Scripture called the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>which enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> John 1.4. ſometimes the Grace of God which teacheth us to deny un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and worldly Luſts, and to walk ſoberly and godly in this preſent world; this is that which hath been often in the mouths of many, though they did not ('tis to be feared) know what it was; therefore whoever thou art that haſt been in ignorance; be it known to thee, that the Grace of God which thou haſt had many times in thy mouth, is Chriſts own ſpirit, which ſpirit hath many times reſtrained thee from committing wickedneſs, for without, thou couldeſt not ſo much as think a good thought much leſs do a good action; for as Chriſt taſted death for every man, he hath given this Heavenly gift to every man, that they may be in a poſſibility of Salvation; ſo that we are not condemned for want of grace; but becauſe we do not improve his gift of Grace, for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to nothing but what his Grace or Spirit will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to perform, if we will but watch when it reproves or inſtructs us.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2d.</label> Some will query thus, how I ſhall know that I have this good Spirit, why may not perſons be deceived and be led by the evil Spirit, whilſt they imagine they are under the guidance of the good one.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95971:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> If thou wilt but enter into a ſerious examination of thy ſelf, thou mayſt call to mind ſome certain times, when thou haſt been under ſome great temptation to commit ſome wicked action; at which time thou haſt had a ſence of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in thy mind that cauſed a great unwillingneſs in thee to proceed, and perhaps giving way to the temptation, thou wert overcome; after which thou haſt had ſome terrour in thy ſelf; now therefore obſerve that which cauſed that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to commit the ſin, was Gods ſpirit, and that which inclined thee to the ſin was the Devils ſpirit; ſo the Tree is known by the fruit; therefore be ſatisfied at whatſoever time thou doſt ſind thy ſelf under temptation, the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus will be always reſſiſting, if thou wilt yield obedience to it, thou ſhalt ſind power ariſing in thee to overcome, the tempter and temptation; by this means thou wilt come to be Spiritually acquainted with Chriſt, and partake of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, ſo that he will be precious to thee; for thou wilt be more in love with him then poſſibly thou couldeſt formerly, and thou wilt certainly know the difference between his ſpirit and the evil ones; becauſe the one enclines thy heart at all times to good, and reſiſts evil: and the other always enclines to evil and reſiſts good; ſo thou needſt not fear being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved if thou art watchful over thy own heart. Friendly Reader, theſe things I write to thee out of pure aſſection, and tender regard I have to Gods Glory, and the everlaſting well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of thy poor immortal Soul; and that thou mayeſt know the difference between profeſſion and poſſeſſion; for there are many that profeſs the name of Chriſt who are altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of him; for though Chriſt is by his ſpirit in every man, yet every man is not in Chriſt; that is, every one hath not taken his good ſpirit for their Guide and Teacher, but have continued rebelling againſt it, in ſo much that they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him to take his good ſpirit from them, and then, not till then, they may be accounted reprobates; for the Lord of life is ſo merciful that he condemns nont, but thoſe who have abuſed his long-ſuffering and forbearance; therefore it behoves every one to beware ſinning out the day of Gods viſitation, in which the tender offers of his love and mercy ere extended to them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
